okay
folks let's
start so today's lecture is on uh Leed
Locomotion and uh we're going to do it
in three parts so the first part will be
Leed Locomotion for
quadrupeds and uh here the leading
approaches now are all based on uh
reinforcement learning and uh I'll uh
talk us through those after that we will
have work on learning to walk for
humanoids and Ilia is going to give a
talk on that and this will end up being
a bias sample the first one is also a
bio sample very much towards Berkeley
work and then the third segment of today
is uh uh basically the MPC trajectory
optimization kind of approach which uh
Boston Dynamics has followed and uh for
that we are going to give you links to
some videos and so forth that you can
watch so I'm not going to be able to
give the lecture all the way to the end
because I have to get on the plane to to
Germany for cor
so okay so let's start so roughly uh 40
minutes on quadrupeds 40 minutes on
humanoids and then homework is uh you
spend spend one and a half hours
watching uh videos on uh uh you know the
Boston Dynamics work on Atlas and and so
on okay does that make sense okay so
let's start with learning to work for
quadrupeds and uh and uh we start with
some
examples and uh I think of this as like
the one of the first really big success
stories
for uh uh learning in robotics in the
modern era I mean where okay because uh
serious people uh I mean there were
papers that were written about uh Leed
Locomotion with learning and so on but
the serious work was all uh you know
Boston Dynamics MPC that kind of work
and uh what changed was really to pieces
of work the first was from eth Zurich
from maroh herter group so they they LED
here they were the first was to show
very effective training of quadrupeds
with reinforcement learning and uh that
was followed by our work which was I
think even more purist in terms of being
purely based on reinforcement learning
with no gate priors and so on
Incorporated so uh so first let me just
show you some results of this quadruped
work so this is a paper which was
presented in 2021 so this is now like
four 3 4 years old and uh uh this
Paradigm now has been replicated in many
Labs so at this point like this is this
it
works and uh what's notable is that this
is just one policy it's exactly the same
policy
okay where is the the the style in the
the people who build MPC controllers is
that they build different controllers
for different kinds of terrains and then
they have a way to switch among them
and here is Locomotion and
navigation so now you do have a camera
so far you had a blind
robot again it has knows nothing about
the environment what it uses what it
uses essentially got a local search for
uh okay so the way I'm going to uh take
you through this is uh in stages uh this
is more or less reflecting the history
of this work where starting with what
was the first version what was the
second version what was the third
version and uh and so
on okay so this is uh training with
reinforcement learning in
simulation and uh I mean the technique
we developed for this is called rapid
motor adaptation and this is led by
Ashish and this was his PhD
thesis so uh so the initial training was
reinforcement learning and simulation
okay and in simulation you have this uh
legged robot walking and what is
important is that you have sufficient
variety so how do you ensure sufficient
variety you need to have sufficient
Variety in the terrain and the way that
is ensured is by this fractal terrain so
you have ups and downs but some ups are
high and some ups are smaller and then
and so forth so you get a very huge
variety of terrain with this kind of
synthetic terrain so you train in
simulation uh and uh what's noteworthy
here is that
uh walking is a particularly good
example here for uh
uh the reinforcement learning Paradigm
why because in the reinforcement
learning Paradigm it's basically a way
to solve the optimal control problem
there's a cost function and we are
trying to find trajectories which
optimize right so it should there should
it should be easy to write down the cost
function that is important the cost
function for making an omelet is not so
easy to write down whereas the cost
function for walking is very easy to
write down what is that basically go
forward use be smooth uh use minimum
energy all right so but with these a
prior considerations you can write down
a cost function for walking and then
reinforcement learning is just a
technique for
finding uh finding solving the
optimization problem I mean you could
solve it in other ways and uh
essentially the Boston Dynamics way is
is another way to solve that
optimization problem it's just the
difference is just the
technique okay uh so I want to now State
some of the philosophy uh which is that
we we took these as starting assumptions
which is that uh unlike past work uh
which was very much gate oriented that
the way you you design controllers for
Gates so walking running Etc and gates
are periodic movements and these have
been popular in in in uh Robotics and
motor control for a while so this this
paper by hilderbrand lists the the gates
for various uh four-legged animals okay
so at a slope so they like Pace Trot
walk Gall things like that and they all
have to do with the pattern of
footfalls and these were also popular in
biological motor control because they
suggest a fairly easy way to implement
because uh what you do is you implement
pattern generators so pattern generators
so essentially you have some neuronal
circuit which is driving each leg and
basically you can have the exactly the
same the same program the same sequence
just shifted in phase for the different
legs right so it gives uh sort of a
neural economy because a fairly small
circuit can can achieve this behavior
and in fact these pattern generators
have been found in many species and it's
not just for walking I mean a fish
swimming or a bird flying right you need
to have this pattern of essentially some
periodic movement of the wings or the
fins or or
whatever so so these ideas are kind of
old 19 this is a 1987 paper here and uh
so the F uh I think there were legged
machines before marre but I think Ohio
people in Ohio had tried to build a
six-legged walking machine but really
the first really big successful effort
which got a lot of attention was the
work of Mark rabbert which is kind of
mid 1980s and 90s and and he's very much
influenced by this uh this pattern
generator uh point of view and uh and if
you uh and this is a point I need to
make repeatedly uh we all tend to think
with oh what can we do today and what
were these people doing at that time and
and you feel oh how why were they doing
such simple stuff why were they not
doing walking robots Okay the way I
showed you five minutes ago so you
always have
to remember in any area of AI the
techniques which we could use in 1980s
and 90s were dictated by the computing
power available then so the computing
power follows M's law so you normally
hear of M law in the forward Direction
but to have sympathy for all these
oldtime researchers such as like Mark
rabbert or me in the 1980s you have to
think of M law backwards which means
that we had to make do with computers
which were 100 million times slower than
today and the fact that we could do
anything interesting you guys should be
appreciative of that right because we
had computers which were like a million
times slower 100 million times slower
something like that okay so uh so that's
why so anyway this is this is Mark
reber's work which is what I think this
paper is 1983 and he was in fact not
even building four legs it was like a
one-legged machine and it is like in
that era with some Hydraulics and not El
you know it was some big Noy machine
which is like jumping up and down you
can probably find videos of that
somewhere which are fun to watch okay
anyway that's 1980s but uh where are we
now uh so when we were doing this work
we were it was already close to uh it
was 2019 2020 and at that point the
hardware situation had become pretty
good because many there were many groups
which had developed good robust Hardware
and uh in fact commercially it was
available so so we we got we bought this
robot from
unry which was available at that time
and we preferred it to something like
spot because uh we had access to the
lowlevel controllers and unitri in fact
also gave was selling these robots at
which were much cheaper because the
previous generation of robots
essentially you're talking $100,000 or
more whereas uh unit
had this robot for
$10,000 so cost plays a role in how how
quickly some stuff gets
adopted okay uh now what's the the uh
what do we know from observations of
human children growing up so these are
some uh
pictures but they're also videos so
these are just like videos that you know
for example parents collect when their
kid first LS to walk it's okay well not
the bottom to uh and uh uh Karen Adolf
Professor Karen Adolf at NYU has done a
lot of research on this and I recommend
her papers to you but this is the figure
which I think I've shown in a previous
lecture but let me replay it so this is
how this girl is learning to walk there
is no gate here there is no running gate
here no walking gate here she's taking
steps uh sideways forwards backwards
right and and that's what we need to
provide the ability for so what that the
the the starting point for for deepak's
work was we we said we are not going to
program in any Gates we're going to have
everything emerge with reinforcement
learning because clearly this kid is not
starting out with a pre-programmed Gates
so that was a distinction with respect
to the the the dominant uh in fact the
first big success C of reinforcement
learning for Locomotion which was the
eth group marter so they start with a
gate and then they learn a residual
policy on that with RL whereas we made
no such
assumption okay so I think this is a
repeat no pre-program gate so this is
like our slogan we are going to follow
this okay next uh approach is uh uh is
uh to train a policy and simulation okay
you know reinforcement learning so that
all
standard uh key uh well the notation
here is X is the state a is the action
and action here is refers to Joint
angles okay desired joint angles in this
case now uh there is a trick here which
was uh used by the the Marco hutter
group and uh was proposed by vladin
Colton in and Philip granul in another
paper which is train with privileged
information so reinforcement learning is
hard because it's a search problem and
then you have to find Solutions which
work in many different parts of the
space and to avoid the the the the
network from getting confused it's good
to give it some guidance and the
guidance here can come from ground truth
knowledge of properties like Mass Center
Mass friction terrain height and so
forth so this is privileged information
which is available at training time and
you can use that okay
and uh in fact what we can do is we can
take that through an encoder so that's
basically compressing it right this
might be like 20 30 parameters but we
can compress it down to five parameters
eight parameters something of that sort
okay uh and what you do is that you are
conditioning the policy on this latent
variable now this is a I think a cool
idea because what this is saying is
I don't need to have exactly the same
policy for every situation so the policy
for walking on flat ground versus policy
for walking in sand policy for walking
uphill downhill these policies can be
different whereas uh traditionally you
would design different controllers here
these policies can be different because
they get this Z input which is capturing
the the situation in these uh in these
different
cases and uh and the Z is going to come
from this encoder of these environmental
parameters okay so so far so good so now
you can have one controller to which is
like the union of all the different
controllers because the Z is doing some
kind of soft
switching okay so we call these the
extrinsics okay uh what's the reward
function so this is essentially an
optimal control problem and
reinforcement learning is solving the
optimal control problem in a certain way
and uh what are you minimizing you're
minimizing uh essentially you don't want
to consume too much energy you want to
not uh you know be smooth move forward
okay it's very straightforward there's
no hackery here which was what people
end up doing in manipulation so one of
the reasons why reinforcement learning
has been less successful in manipulation
tasks is because just specifying the
task is much
harder okay
okay so now we have trained this robot
and it has fallen a lot but then it
learns to work okay and then uh and now
we wanted to walk in the real world and
what's the and this is where this
technique which we call RMA rapid motor
adaptation comes in and this comes down
to this problem of what is the Z so at
training time you have you know the Z
because you have this encoder which has
access to privileged information about
the terrain and as well as some
properties of the robot but at test time
I mean there's a blind robot walking in
different are how does it know this Z is
not known so how do we uh so so the the
idea here is let's run another neural
network which is going to try to
estimate the Z and this other neural
network the way it works is that it uh
it it has to make use of some bigger
uh temporal history of the movement so
uh why is that reasonable well when
you're walking on ground you on some
ground you're going to apply some forces
and torqus and so forth right now the
consequences of that will vary depending
on the kind of terrain and that gives
you a signal of what kind of terrain you
are
in so uh so we have to estimate this
online and this is done by this neural
network called the adaptation module so
both of these are like small networks
the base policy is a small multi-layer
percepton the adaptation module is
another small Network I mean uh so what
what this is doing is it has access to
this temporal history so 50 50 steps
worth and with that and that so it knows
what is the state and what are the what
were the desired actions and from that
it's trying to estimate what situation
you are
and this training of the adaptation
module can be done in in simulation so
in fact training this is a supervised
learning problem because you have a z
which you can estimate from privileged
information with that encoder and now
that becomes the
target uh for training so that's what is
indicated here so phase one you train
with privileged information that you
only have available at simulation time
in phase two you are preparing for when
you are going to be working in the real
world and you don't have access to all
this privileged information and you do
that by training this adaptation module
and this is a supervised learning
problem much easier we know in in
machine learning that supervised
language problems are much easier than
reinforcement learning problem so this
is easy and that's what is shown
here so so three different modules are
being trained base policy the that's
your essentially your RL right uh okay
environmental Factor encoder it's
essentially the uh features of the like
these some 25 parameters of the
environment compressed down to some five
or eight and the adaptation module is a
network which uh you which has the
temporal history so you could implement
it with an lstm or whatever which has
some temporal history and then it tries
to predict the C
okay and that's it now you're ready to
run this in real time and then we get
this policy one policy which works in
all
setting okay I think we have seen that
before analysis or adaptation molecule
module okay so this is uh supposed to
help you understand what's going on so
uh I think uh so the experiment is uh
there's some olive oil being put spread
on a mattress with on a it is covered
with a plastic
sheet and then let's look at the the dog
the dog's legs also have a plastic sock
so you're trying to make the job hard
plastic on plastic with
oil okay and then as the dog
walks What's happen
withs and then it
recovers let's watch it again
yeah so I mean if you think about it
intuitively when you're are walking on
slippery ground like on some Icy surface
versus walking on dry ground you you
walk slightly differently you walk more
carefully right okay and uh that's what
we want the robot to do at some level
well but how do you as a human know what
to do well you have eyes so you look and
you say this is icy ground and this is
sand and this is a flat Road and you
change your strategy this robot is blind
it can't do that so what can it do it
has to infer from its own past history
and its own past history is it commands
some actions and then it there's an
actual State change so that's what's
going to happen and uh uh the way it's
going to improve its performance the way
it's going to adapt is by the estimation
of Z so as it moves and it's on the
slippery ground it estimates the Z and
the bet once it has the correct Z it'll
the that's an input to the policy and
the policy will
change no not exactly the oily surface
because we just train it on uh uh on a
fractile surface with varying kinds of
parameters of like friction and so on so
there's never exact same circumstances
those are not that's not possible what
you need is something which is similar
to it okay and then it has to work so uh
because we cannot possibly create all
the possible physical conditions that
exist in the world for walking right in
the simulator but what you need are
equivalent so my uh model for this is
metamers metamers as in color so in
color or in color vision what happens is
that there can be two different spectral
distributions of Light which give rise
to the same color response in the in the
three types of cones that we have right
and so there so there can be two lights
which are not the same but to the human
eye they appear the same because their
projection on the on the response
functions of the three cone types are
exactly the same so that's that may be
something which helps you to think about
this so here uh what's happening is you
look at these
variable Z1 Z5 so these are some of the
components of that Z Vector which is H
dimensional and uh you'll see this red
curve which is high and then it becomes
less and the blue curve at the bottom it
goes the other way around and that's
essentially happening as the robot is
struggling so let's see
this so it's struggling and then the Z
value is getting changed and when then
the new Z is applied to the walking
policy it starts
and then here something else which is if
robot is and you throw 5 kg this 5 kg is
a big deal because this robot is 8 kgs
okay so so therefore so what happens
here again is in
slowmo again some variables in this case
Z2 and z7 they sort of capture how the
situation will change and then the robot
uh starts to walk better and in fact if
you look at this variable called knee
toow which is kind of in the middle
essentially that changes so you're
applying greater torqus which you need
to because you're you're you're more
mass to
carry and uh okay so this is so we have
uh so now you can take do the so now you
do the in research you should do
experiments to better understand what
you did and ablation studies are a
canonical example you you change some
you delete some module and see whether
how it works this is uh this is how RMA
works but now suppose you you you did
not have this adaptation
module okay okay and and here's another
one so this is the mattress so note
again there was no mattress in the
training right it's just that there was
something equivalent to it because of
the the variety of ter so this is how
the robot walk
matches and uh without
adaptation okay and then uh and then it
works better than
controller all these stories have the
same ending it's the RMA controller
which works and the other one dies
okay so
okay goodbye okay
okay okay okay and then you can show
some results so I won't go through all
the numbers but mean uh
but the the the impressive part really
is this adaptation I think and then
subsequently this algorithm has been
applied in other settings okay and then
there are some numbers which I'll skip
okay and then various so we did a lot of
experiments on uh RMA without the
adaptation in different settings some
experiments are done in synthetic
conditions some are done in physical
condition so good research requires
doing a lot of experiments and they
should be
and both done in Sim in simulation
because you have more control and you
should do them in the physical one okay
okay so that's version two version three
version three is uh how do we get it to
walk at different speeds okay turns out
this is kind of trivial okay why is it
trivial it's trivial because you one of
the the terms in the loss function is uh
walking at a you you you you get more
credit for walking
uh at the desired speed so when you're
walking very slow you you can get more
credit by walking faster but once you
have hit the desired speed you don't get
any credit for walking
faster so you can just train controllers
for differing different desired speeds
you can also train controllers for
different angular velocity so this way
you can get the robot to rotate and uh
and then you can distill it all into one
common policy so sometimes this is a
good trick you train different versions
because RL is finicky so you you you you
it's easier in a in a more restricted
setting you will make it work and then
you distill it okay and then uh that's
it uh and then here are results so uh
different desired speeds and now uh what
you'll see here uh with all these solid
blocks uh so it's uh right front left
front
front right rear left rear okay so those
are the four rows they C so when you
have it filled in that means that the
foot is on the ground when it's uh White
space that means that the leg is in the
air so when it's walking slowly most of
the time most of the feet are on the
ground as you go to the extreme right
you see that the amount of time on the
ground is reduced and the amount of time
in the air is increased and these are
the gates that you get
okay oh sorry I should have let it go
through
now it's really
happen Okay and then why did we get
different Gates uh well this is the
point of this paper that turns out that
uh that uh different gates are more
energetically efficient at different
speeds and we talked about this earlier
in the course with respect to humans for
walking and running so the same is true
for horses and the same is true for and
then these are
some so it's stand
of any I skip this
okay now uh now this is
yeah for what
purpose some yeah some duration in the
past how long should it be basically on
the order of a gate cycle
yeah I mean in in Walking there's a very
natural unit of time which is sort of
the gate cycle right in that you will
get all the information and then it
should should be
repeated so a couple of
seconds yeah so it'll be if suppose you
have yeah so so you put in as many time
steps as needed for capturing the I mean
your control is operating at a certain
rate so okay so there's some subtlety
here which I didn't go into which is
this uh RL policy doesn't operate at
1,00 Hertz right it it's much slower
because there's a lot of compute
involved so it's operating at a slower
rate than the PD controllers at the
level of the the joints so those are
operating at more like 100 htz or 500 I
don't know the exact don't remember the
exact number okay and uh so that's the
the policy and this adaptation is
actually operating even
slower okay but it it it's it's it can
be slow but it cannot take one minute in
one minute you will fall see humans we
we recover if I sleep a little bit then
I recover I move my hands and I recover
what's the time scale of that it's on
the order of a second okay if I if I
took 10 seconds to reorient my body I'll
fall if but I do not need it to be
recovered in 0.1 second I mean it's just
I mean
physics that's what is happening here
okay this is uh combining navigation
with
Locomotion and uh this uh turned out to
be quite straightforward so we have this
policy which you can say go in a
particular direction so this is now a
hierarchical controller so the lowest
layer can do the walking in any
particular direction
and uh what you need to do is to tell it
which direction to go and the direction
in which to go is given by uh
essentially what's free space and you
can use the ideas from the navigation
so it's yeah so this is just classical
ideas for obstacle avoidance I mean you
can so this is why navigation is not so
hard it's really looking locally where
is free space you go in that direction
you do not need a complete map of the
environment
okay uh okay uh and then uh okay here
okay here's some little trick which is
that when you are on sickly ground then
you should walk
slower and uh uh essentially the robot
when it on the planks it walks slower
okay how do we achieve that it's pretty
easy what you do is you have an
estimator for the probability of a fall
which you can train in simulation and
the probability of a fall is higher when
you're walking faster right so the robot
starts to walk it's always running this
estimator of the probability of a fall
and this probability of fall has gone to
high has gone high so you start to walk
slower and then the probability to fall
comes down and that's it and that
results in safe walking behavior and
it's I mean something that we would do
right uh okay Vision uh this is what a
vision model
does okay so what do you think went
wrong here
it's glass is transparent so the vision
system doesn't see the glass
okay okay this works much better why
because Pro means that you're using the
joint angle so when it when you are
trying to move and you are not moving
you know that you are you must have hit
some kind of a w so uh
seems
after
yeah okay and then uh fall predictor
Collision detector okay so uh okay it's
going to say Vision
appropriate okay let's see what it does
for vision and P
I mean there exact Behavior not
programmed so it it looks pretty clever
but it just it's obvious it's just
looking for white
space okay
okay okay I think I keep more
Vis we tried it in a lots of places it
works okay now the last part of my
quadruped talk oh I think I was no it's
okay 40 minutes I'm
only uh is using vision for uh movement
in the obstacles in the vertical domain
so think of obstacles as being in the
horizontal plane so there you just uh
rotate your direction of movement right
so you just use your you you you move in
a different direction now what about the
obstacles which are in the vertical
Direction like stairs and so on now you
have to change your movement in the
vertical Direction okay so that's that's
what this paper is about and this is the
last bit that I want to talk
about and uh okay this is saying who
else had worked on
Locomotion why do we need Vision we need
vision for these difficult situations
okay so here I want to make a a point
which is worthwhile which is what's the
classical robotics way of doing it and
what was the way that we developed so
the classical robotics way of doing it
is build a map that's what classical
robotics people do they they believe in
you know State estimation and uh the way
the vision is used is you build a map so
therefore youve got your robot moving
it's got a camera you try to build a map
and the map can be built in a more
detailed way not just 2D but also 3D
okay and what's the problem with that I
mean in theory this is fine in practice
it doesn't work so well why does it not
work so well because there's this uh uh
and you discover it when you do real
world experiments is that your your
robot and Camera are shaking right your
robot is shaking your camera is shaking
what that means is that each
individual uh data that you have
captured is good but when you try to fit
it together you have got all this noise
because from one the the pose the
rotation and translation of the camera
from one frame to the next I mean that's
taking place and you do not have an
accurate estimate of it so you put it
all together what's going to happen is
your resulting map is going to be noisy
okay and then so that will happen in the
real world and now what do you do in
your simulator well in the simulator you
if you don't do anything you're going to
be in trouble so what you do is in the
Similator you add synthetic noise to
your maps and this results in not so
good behavior it results in suboptimal
Behavior so uh so yeah so anyway so if
you want to see the comparison here you
can look at the work from uh Marco
Herter's group where they use this map
type approach and uh so they they they
were pretty successful I mean you look
at all their deployments but we wanted
to show off and we wanted to find a
setting which was hard enough that their
technique wouldn't necessarily work but
ours would work and this
is okay it's the same policy but the
interes demo is this one lots of people
can go up and down stairs but this going
on
okay and note that it doesn't know
environment in advance and you can
rearrange okay so this is an easier
version of the problem say are easier
than going on the tools okay I I I think
I've shown this video a million times
but so okay how you how you train this
system so again idea of privileged
information is good so at training time
you give the robot access to the depths
at a bunch of points near in the
neighborhood of the robot and it uses
that for training and uh the philosophy
is a little bit like
RNN little bit like RMA but now
capturing the geometry of the
environment so the the geometry of the
environment is being so there is this Z
variable which is which is the latent
variable which captures some of the
physics parameters gamma is a latent
geometry parameters and that's
essentially what's the information you
need to know for foot placement okay by
the way this foot placement that we have
here it emerges in this part of this
policy the most more classical way like
the again the Boston Dynamics type of
style what they would do is they will
first be thinking about foot placement
so very consciously you figure out where
to put my left foot then to put my right
foot so there's a like a planner which
is figuring out foot placement and then
there is your MPC controller which is
executing on the movement of the body
and something about this seems wrong
right when you are if I spent my entire
ire life when I was walking planning my
foot placements okay I mean I I do all
my thinking when I'm walking and it's
because my uh I'm not using my planning
capabilities to figure out where to put
my next foot okay so anyway
philosophically it seems this planner
approach is wrong okay in reinforcement
learning we can do it differently you
try I mean as always you have a lot of
variety in your terrains blah blah blah
okay I'm skipping the details here you
start with an rgbd camera and then you
is a spirit of RMA but extended not to
capture these geometric parameters of
the
ter and
uh you look I mean I I think the cool
part is that the rear for lands up not
on the ground but on
a I mean of course you have the
information in the front but you have
kept enough public
it so I think Boston Dynamic spot is
being tested in like millions of hours
of walking but
I I I don't know if they have a demo of
walking
on so they
do okay and then we also claim that uh
this robot can climb up so it figures
out this trick of lifting its leg off on
the side and this is the power of RL see
you wouldn't get this with imitation
learning you need in reinforcement
learning can discover new Solutions
because it's it's search
and then uh so
this so it really tries hard look at
this I think this on the right you'll
get some interive
result see when I see this dog I really
get this sense of it is trying hard it's
of course just a computer
program so we anthropomorphize map free
okay so previously our slogan was gate
free then our slogan was map free so map
free gate
free and then uh and then oh yeah
numbers okay then here I have to so at
the end I have to end with blooper so
this is a
blooper and this is that was supposed to
be another blooper let me see if I can
get it to
so on these stool type things I think in
tries we done okay it worked like nine
out of 10 so this is I think that
failure and I'll end here and now I is
going to tell you about humanoids which
is a harder so I think quadrupeds are
solved we can do quadruped I mean people
have done work after that on parkour and
so on but it's the same Machinery I
think the ideas here just they robust
they work okay humanoids is harder
because walking on two legs is harder
than walking on four legs so Ilia will
entertain you
now let's give people a two minute break
right but you can plug in okay let me
exit
the yeah yeah there's a zoom session
which you can get to uh from uh from the
website yeah yeah
yeah so to get the right display first
log to zoom then put
your
yeah
e
e let see that I Tor do we do we have
the zoom thing
working maybe to chat yeah yeah okay got
it yeah it's good
yeah
okay sure sure
did we do the two minutes is okay yeah
we done okay so so we've seen in the
first part of the lecture right we've
seen a lot about quadri right and now we
like to to talk about humanoids um but I
thought it might be worthwhile to sort
of think about these two a little bit so
if you think of of a blunder Beetle
robot right you have this big body that
has a lot of mass and then it has four
relatively light F in comparison with
the
body
so so that means that essentially as the
legs move it sort of impacts the the
body less now in contrast if you look at
the humanoid it has sort of bipedal so
it's easier to lose balance it has heavy
legs it has a big heavy torso with a lot
of mass and inertia and as you sort of
move you're moving that mass inera
around you need to essentially um it's
much harder to to maintain balance so
that makes this problem considerably
more challenging than the problem of
quadrupedal
locomotion um but nevertheless there's
been a lot of work in this area and I'll
show a few of my favorite
examples um so first here's this U robot
called Asimo from uh from a Japanese
manufacturer Bond so what's interesting
is theyve started working on this
research program in the 80s and they
sort of kept it secret undercover for
think about a decade and then at some
point the Japanese government was sort
of starting this big research effort and
humanist they're like oh by the way we
have this thing and it's it's pretty
good and of course this is not their
their early version this is one of their
latest versions and you can sort of see
it's pretty cool it could do a bunch of
things and it could work and you know
this is not the first development human
inter of course but um this was one that
I was stre
um and then another another reason why I
I sort of pointed out this one is
because the walking in this case is
based on this principle called zero
moment point or zmp for short so this is
really an old idea it comes it was first
published in the in the 1968 and it was
sort of done purely computationally
without a hardware proof the hardware
proof came later in the 70s in Japan uh
but it has been the basis of this ASIMO
robot and it's you know my guess would
be also being used in the today's sort
of latest and greatest humanoid um
efforts like you know figure and Tesla
and so on is still sort of u based on
this technology largely and kind of and
and what's the tell right so so we'll
add we'll give you these details you can
see but the basic of the tell is this
flat foot walking where one leg is
always stable on the ground so you
you'll notice in this video that the
robot is sort of always has one leg on
the ground and it's sort of doing a
little bit of hip movements to uh to
correct for the uh for the rotation and
let's see another let's look at another
Asim video and S of focusing on that and
you s of really distinctly see this and
now of course coupled with some sort of
obstacle avoidance but focus on the gate
um and you'll very clearly see this and
and now if you sort of you know given
this you look at the you know your
figure video your Tesla video it's not
it's sort of it had if there's some
similarities with this these classes of
approaches and of course they've been
extended and improved and so on but so
of the basic principle is there uh so
now the challenge with something like
this right is that you have this uh this
distinction between you know food
planning that gend I mentioned earlier
and walking and it's very hard to get
really Dynamic uh motions with something
like this uh but of course we've all
seen um Atlas Dynamics videos sorry
Atlas robot videos from Boston Dynamics
and I don't think we can uh have a human
right lecture without showing one of
those uh but what's really interesting
here is that this is super Dynamic right
so like this robot is running around
doing parkour jumping uh going over
obstacles and so on U and super super
impressive right so like very um s a
completely a different league and the
step functioning capabilities compared
to the previous video I've shown um and
what enables this well as jendra
mentioned earlier this is enabled by
model predictive controler MPC for short
and this is something that Boston
Dynamics has been sort of really pushing
um pushing for for a while now and we'll
I think include a few videos from Scott
and other folks at B Dynamics on um and
so you can sort of see uh hear from the
the leading Institute in this area uh
but yeah but this class is about
learning U Learning robots or robots
that learn so I think for the rest of
the lecture we'll we'll focus more on
learning
approaches and you might also ask well I
guess once you see this and sort of in
the context of the um quadruped word of
jendra has mentioned right sort of two
questions po pop out i' like so the
first question is um you know isn't this
sold right this looks amazing it can
jump and can sort of go around like is
is this it right why haven't we seen
robots in the real world why don't we
yet have humanoid robots around us um
and then the part of the answer there is
that these approaches are really good in
structured environments so as long as
you sort of know the environment you
have a very good sense of perception you
can sort of essentially recreate a map
then these these approaches tend to work
really well uh but they struggle with
generalizing and adapting to new
environments or variations of seene
environments and that's sort of why you
actually haven't seen very many videos
of Atlas out being sort of in the wild
or really seeing Atlas outside the the
Boston Dynamics office um and so that's
sort of one um and then the point number
two question number two my task is well
we've seen the quadrupeds quadrupedal
robots are doing really great like they
can go in a robot can go basically
anywhere so why are these robots not
there can't we just of rerun the same
thing and and and S of that that the
answer that is a little bit more nuanced
and I think has a lot to do with the
extra challenges of humanoid robots but
you know in principle we should be able
to have some sort of a learning
technique um that should enable us to
get to the same level of capabilities
but with humanoid
robots and um and then so for the rest
of this um lecture I'll show you some
progress we've made towards that goal um
and um so it starts with this work on
real world human Lo promotion which was
a collaboration with a couple of groups
here at Berkeley and um here is a video
of our robot walking around Berkeley
campus so uh this is a digit robot
developed by agility robotics so it's a
company out of Oregon um so we don't
build Hardware as you might have guessed
but we purchase this software shelf
hardware and then we develop our own
software uh so what you can see here is
a robot uh that's walking and being
controlled by a neural network a single
neural net uh that's running on board
and it's um getting access to the pro
receptive state of the robot and it's
predicting the the future actions um so
it does not use perception it's
completely blind it doesn't use lighter
it doesn't use depth it's it's fully
blind and it's um and it's being um and
all of these videos are a single
policy so how is this achieved uh well
this is achieved through an endtoend
Lear in approach that's based on a
Transformer model that takes us in with
a propriate receptive history of
interleaved observations and actions and
then it predicts the next action and
that's it so so here the observations
are joint positions joint velocities IMU
um Imus of the base and then the actions
are the desired joint
positions um so so so this is very much
in spirit of RMA the the G represented
in the Contex of quadrip and you can
think of this as sort of being a a
slightly more endtoend version of that
where but the the pr sort of the
philosophy the the sort of the things we
want to achieve are very much the same
and
aligned um now like before this is
trained entirely in simulation so here
you can see thousands of different
robots being U simulated in in slightly
different terrains using slightly
different Dynamics
properties uh we train this the these
robots on mostly gentle terrains so it's
sort of mostly flat with a little bit of
slope um and a little bit of these rough
terrains um and then each robot is sort
of also um has randomized properties of
its body of its masses frictions and so
on and then the intuition is if we can
train a single neural net to control all
of these different robots uh then
perhaps it will also work in the real
world because we you can kind of think
of the real world as being sort of yet
another
simulation um and that's that's kind of
the hypothesis so once we train the
model in this in this terrains we deploy
to the real world zero shots so we do
not perform any fine tuning or any
updates uh in the real world is just
being deployed entirely zero shot um and
so in addition to sort of walking
working forward this model can walk uh
this approach enables walking in any
directions it's it's conditioned on
these velocity commands that standard
has described earlier and then you know
by supplying different desired commands
you can achieve walking in different
direction
uh one interesting thing we noticed is
is this emergent arm swing so so a robot
is sort of swings its arms like a human
as a human is walking and um and this is
something that we haven't pre-programmed
but it's also kind of interesting and
you know if you think of human walking
it's somewhat of a peculiar
characteristic of you know why do we
swing our arms this way it's not it's
not entirely obvious um and it turns out
that this is something that has been
studied a lot in um in various different
areas and there are various hypothesis
for why we're doing that but the one
that seems most likely under the
experimental data is that that we swing
our arms to preserve energy so this is a
really nice study from Stanford where
they compared different walking Styles
uh in terms of the how the arms are
moving and it turns out that essentially
if you're um if you're swinging your
arms in a dynamic in normal fashion you
you save the most energy um and this was
sort extra interesting to us because one
of our reward terms for training our
model is to minimize energy now of
course we don't have a causal
relationship here that that that is
indeed what causes this Behavior but
it's an interesting uh observation it's
also an interesting um I think it
suggests an interesting use of these um
is a reinforcement learning models or
computational models really to to verify
these hypothesis about about human
movement um another really interesting
Behavior we' observed is adaptation so
consider the following experiment we
have this robot that's going to walk
over a Terrain that consists of three
sections so walking on flat walking down
slope and then walking on flat again so
let's see what happens so the robot
starts by lifting its legs then in
transitions into this gate of sort of
stepping slowly um and then it goes back
to walking sort of lifting its legs
again on flat now it's interesting is
that we have not pre-programmed this
Behavior this is entirely emergent uh we
haven't encouraged this in in any way we
haven't specified this in the reward
function there's nothing really that
tells the model to do this it sort of
emerges as a byproduct of training um
and and it's also this was really nice
to see because this ability to adapt
actions based on context is really quite
fundamental to human working and um here
is an experiment from um from human
babies from Professor Karen adult theend
I mentioned before where you can see if
the baby sort of walking on flat ground
it doesn't change its gate but now let's
what happens if we slightly change the
slope so now the the baby changes this
game so our robot is not quite that
adaptive but still adaps a little bit uh
let's see what happens if we changed
even
more so so we can't do that yet but U is
a good idea this is really seems like a
a proper is very important and I really
recommend reading the um this work it's
really really really nice and so points
out many experiments like this um and uh
so but if we look at the experimental
data from our experiment um we see a few
interesting things so we see that there
are certain patterns of neural activity
that corresponds to to different
features of the environment so here for
example this neuron neuron 82 is just
like really a unit in the network that
we're and we're plotting it response
over time so what we see is the
responses are sort of flating more when
the robot is lifting it like more and
then they're fling less when the robot
is lifting it fles less then next this
neuron 108 um is high when the terrain
is flat and is low and the terrain is
sloped um and then finally in aggregate
if we visualize the neural activity of
this model we see that the activations
cluster naturally into these two groups
based on the Terin that the model is
training on so this suggest that these
uh the neural representations of this
Transformer model are able to capture
something about the environment um
that's that's relevant to working now we
don't have a causal relationship that
says that the model is indeed changing
actions because it is able to do this um
but it would be interesting to that
would be an interesting thing to study
but we do see that the representations
correlate strongly with the with the
changes in the
terrain um here is another interesting
example of of Behavior so this is this
is a little bit like the the hi
abduction behaviors you see in the case
of the quadruped where because the model
is uh the model first tries to perform a
maneuver it fails and then in subsequent
attempts it changes its action through
swing is like faster and higher to
achieve the desired
goal um so so in summary we've seen a
fully learning based approach for um uh
for human Locomotion and we've seen some
really nice properties in terms of
adaptation with Transformers and um this
these things together have enabled us to
deploy this controller to the real
world um okay but so now we've seen U
we've seen results that were in the real
world uh but they were largely on gentle
terrains so they were large they sort of
mostly flat sometimes a little bit of
slope up to a few degrees Sometimes some
easy over overground obstructions but
not really nowhere near as challenging
as the results we've seen in the case of
quadrupeds which which then really
brings this question of okay um can we
extend the same approach to more
challenging terrains right like could we
do the same thing like could be could we
sort of you know include more complex
terrains in simulation run the program
for longer and and sort of get the model
it can walk anywhere so so in principle
yes um there's no reason why this should
not happen uh but in practice there are
many challenges uh because you know the
problem becomes harder terrains to
simulate are harder reward functions
become harder and all of these
challenges are are mutually reinforcing
which sort of makes the overall problem
harder um so so we take a step back um
and we ask okay can we um can we take
the same architecture but train it in a
slightly different way so concretely
here um we we we study if we can train
the same Transformer controller but
using sequence modeling instead of
reinforcement learning um and we do this
by proposing this framework that has
three parts so so first we need some
sort of a data set in order to be able
to train this model um next we have the
model that's trained on this data and
then finally when this model is trained
we deploy it into the real world um and
then I'll discuss each of these three in
turn so on the data set side we um we
essentially compile a large collection
of walking trajectories that come from
various sources uh so we consider
trajectories from our previous neural
network controller that gives us full
access to both observations and actions
we we access the trajectories from a
model based controller that's a
proprietary controller that we can only
access um the state of as well as Mo up
sequences of humans and videos of humans
um so a few things to notice here so one
is that there's this distinction between
um sequences that have actions and
sequences that do not have actions um
and this is important because there is
more information in sequence with
actions and actions are really um what
at the end of the day we care about and
we want to be able to learn um and then
the second thing to notice here is that
the morphologies are different and the
sort of the um the accuracy of data is
different so in the case of the data
that comes from the same robot well then
the morphology is matching and that's
great but in the case of dat it comes
from humans and and videos the
morphologies are different the the POS
estimation problem to sort of lift human
videos into um into motion sequences
introduces errors and which in turn
introduce noise and so on um okay but
I'd like to highlight the the internet
videos data a little bit because I think
that one really interesting uh so here
you can see um you know two videos of
you know human walking or human running
and you can see
reconstructions um recovered by by
computer vision techniques and developed
by Jatan shubam and other folks in the
lab um and you can see that they you
know they're not perfect there's like a
little bit of jit but they're sort of
they're are pretty good um and and then
you can use these trajectories um to re
kinematically retarget the robot
morphology onto the human trajectories
um and you know these these retargeting
and these reconstructions aren't going
to be perfect but that's okay because
our our technique um sort of does not
require them to be perfect we're not
interested in mimicking these exact
trajectories we're interesting in
acquiring general purpose skills from
the collections of trajectories like
this um and because of that we can
tolerate noise and it's okay if the data
is imperfect it's okay if the data is
noisy and it's sort of one of the big
lessons of deep learning that um you
know we prefer scale even with noise
over small amounts of data that's
perfect and then we we have a way to
train with all of these different
trajectories in a unified fashion um
here are some results of this approach
so what you can see is a controller now
that's exactly the same architecture as
before for it has been trained in a
different way and is deployed to the
real world here in this case planning
the different locations in San
Francisco and um so you can it's still
mostly on gentle terrains
please yeah it was it was roughly equal
uh the data source is the most important
is the one with actions of course other
sources help but the one with accid is
the most important
one I think it's sort of an open
question to see uh remains an open
question to see how far we can push this
by sort of really scaling the the
internet data uh sort of to aot muchar
so so this approach with no
reinforcement learning there's no RL
here
compared like
to um yeah so this works this is super
scalable super easy super simple like
you can train this model in half an hour
on only 2 hours of data uh you know in
comparon the RL model very finicky it
takes about a day or two so that's sort
of the the the that's the benefit you
get from sequence modeling and I I'll
get into the tradeoffs
forly um but then you know and another
thing that's sort of nice is that if you
look at the if you carefully sort of
look at the um the Gate of this model
and the one before you'll you'll notice
that this one's slightly softer and this
this becomes really clear when you run
them in the real world because of the uh
the noise is the tell the audio really
lets you distinguish these different
different
policies um and one thing that we really
pleased to see is that the prediction
error that is this objective correlates
pretty strongly with The Walking
performance as measured by walking
metrics like velocity tracking and and
so on um another nice experiment we uh
we did is sort of we wanted to study to
which extent can this model generalize
to unseen um behaviors so we took a
bunch of trajectories of walking forward
we trained the model on that and then
the test time we prompted the model with
walking backward which was not seen
during training and the model can still
perform those behaviors which was which
was interesting to
see how do you prompt the model to
uh you you supply the desired velocity
command so forward versus backward would
be the sign so you know plus one m/s is
walking forward 1 met per second minus 1
met per second is walking backwards
that uh yeah
yeah um so so in summary we've seen that
we can C the problem of real world human
Locomotion as a pure next token
prediction problem
um and that enables us to train with
various sources of data uh and gives us
a a model that we can then deploy onto a
real humanoid robot and have it walk in
different areas in San
Francisco okay so um you're going back
to the question um you raised earlier
how does this compare to reinforcement
learning right there're trade-offs uh so
so this approach is far more sample
efficient and stable uh which is really
nice so we can this Ser has all of the
appealing properties of uh of sequence
modeling that we've seen really flourish
in the domains like language and vision
um but then the challenge right is that
we cannot get new behaviors truly new
behaviors um because the skills that we
can learn are limited to the skills that
we have seen in Prior data uh so there
there's no Freel lunch um really the
tool the only tool that we have today
that can give us something that's truly
novel and truly new is reinforcement
learning but then you know it comes with
all of these these tradeoffs um so so
then we we really in in this latest work
we've asked if we can combine the
benefits of these two different
paradigms to see if we can get something
better uh and specifically we propose an
approach that consists of two steps so
in step one we pre-train the model with
sequence modeling so this is exactly the
same as the most recent work I presented
um and then the intuition is that even
if this model is not the most capable
one it'll it'll give us a good starting
point for acquiring new skills
um and and the the way we will acquire
new skills is through reinforcement
learning in simulation uh so we first
pre-train a model with equal moding and
then we find unit with RL in simulation
um so so what's the intuition the
intuition is that you know even the
robot that can only walk on flat ground
should be more efficient in learning how
to walk up a slope than a robot that
cannot walk at all right so that's kind
of the intuition and and you know
quantitatively this this sort of matches
what we what we observe in in EXP
experiments and we find un it in in
simulation in a Moko simulator using
various terrains I'll discuss them a
little bit later and then again same as
before once it's training simulation we
deploy it to the real world um and and
we really wanted to see um how good is
this controller actually in in real
world environments so rather than sort
of
um handpicking a few different terrains
we we really wanted to take it to
something that's representative of the
terrains that the human with walk on and
one one natural um case of those are
hikes so we took this robot on five real
human hikes and we've um and we've sort
of just completed them in total that's
been over four miles of hiking so you
might recognize some of them the
inspiration Trail the Belgium Trail and
I'm only showing three here and I'll
show you some Snippets from those hikes
so this is this was the Belgium Trail at
towards the very top um so this was this
was about um 1.1 miles of hiking about
took close to two hours um and and the
robot can sort of was uh able to
successfully navigate these different
terrains here's a something that's a bit
harder so here we have a slope uh with L
and Rocky terrain uh and this is in the
panoramic Trail I think the video Ross
um but you can also see all of these on
the on the website um but then so you
know natural environments are one source
of challenging terrains another source
are man-made environments and and in in
that aspect we're fortunate to be near
San Francisco which probably has some of
the hardest man-made environments for
walking um and we went to various steep
streets in San Francisco and we
evaluated our robots here I'm showing a
few Snippets from the Russian Hill
neighborhoods I'm showing the percent
grade on the on the top left of each
image so so to calibrate you the ones
that you can see in the top right about
31% grade so these are are about the
steepest streets in San Francisco the
steepest would be 31. 2.8 um sort of
less a little bit less than 32% grade so
this is super Steep and this is hard for
healthy human adults as well U going up
the up these streets and this robot can
sort of go up can turn on the slope can
go down um had no falls on any of these
um and it can sort of navigate all of
these without problems let me show you a
few videos of that um so here's one
video of going up so this is uh this is
overlooking alcatra you can see in the
back
um and the here's one of those really
steep ones here you can see the Bay
Bridge so this is the Broadway
Avenue and this is 31% per grade you can
also see the cars the cars are pretty
pretty sled yeah um okay so what's
interesting is that um we see that
different Gates emerge for different
slope types so whether the robot is
walking on flat is walking uphill it's
walking downhill it's using a different
uh it's using a different gate and you
can sort of measure that by looking at
the U The Joint positions of of a couple
of these critical joints over the gate
cycle and again this was is completely
emergent we haven't pre-programmed this
or encouraged it in any way um and
another thing that's interesting is that
when we find un this model we only find
unit on Rigid terrains so only flat um
slopes discrete obstacles rough he so
sort of um all everything here is rigid
there's nothing that's soft there's
nothing that's deformable uh but then we
deploy this robot on Sand um and this is
this is pretty deep
sand and you can see that the robot can
still um it still figures out how to
adjust its movements to maintain balance
and avoid the
fall um we and also go through grow
through water so in retrospect this was
a pretty expensive
experiment but likely it
worked and um yes it's it's all of these
are unseen and it is really interesting
because there's nothing in simulation
that's simulating soft deformable um
it's all it's all rigid it's all
entirely rigid and you know it's
conceivable that some combination of of
of forces
really simulate something it's a little
bit like walking on rid but still I'd
say that there is a big big domain Gap
here um and
uh
comp yeah we have not done that
yet uh I mean it be it work uh you know
the the interesting thing is that if you
were to sample your Pine model you put
it back in pre-training you would be
able to absorb those skills very
efficiently but there would still be new
behaviors that you wouldn't get you know
you couldn't learn to say walk upstairs
that way because that would be sort of
something that's entirely new um so I
think sequence modeling is really great
at absorbing what's already in the data
but it is very unlikely to give you
something that's truly novel and truly
new um reinforcement learning I think is
the only tool we have for that
than
exe this is entirely in what was learn
of reinforcement is just the idea like
the pre- tring just help you be more
sample yeah so so pre-training really
helps you with sample efficiency is the
main is the main help it's not only
sample efficiency it's also sort of
determines your starting point such that
um it becomes easier to optimize from
there and your reward problem is a
little bit easier because you already
sort of kind of know how to walk uh but
these behaviors are not seen even during
fine tuning so this is this is Al to
distribution and uh yeah and then then
the sand example is pretty interesting
because um here we do an experiment
where we walk on fail first and then we
transition into sand so and you know as
a human you would expect that's right as
you're walking through sand you need to
lift your you need to exort more energy
you need to LIF in order to lift your
legs to the same position and and we see
this here experimentally in a sense that
if you look at the middle plot you see
that the in both cases the robot is
reaching the same positions but if you
look at the third plot you see that it's
using more torque to do so on Sand um
and this is an example of dynamic
adaptation
to Terin
type um and and and the robot is very
robust to external
disturbances um so and and this is
pretty hard because it's also it's
slightly slowed it's uneven um and uh
yeah and it can sort of it gets this
recovery behavior of sort of putting it
like in the back um now to to give you a
little bit of context what happened here
is um but in training did you supply
these both kinds of system with it yeah
with it so so this is not as you is is a
um saying this is not that
surprising that they would be it would
be this robust but it's sort of
something that's pretty hard to get with
let's say you know traditional
approaches but also the like the
sequence modeling approach that we
describ would have a really hard time
getting something like
this um but yeah but what happened here
essentially is that the joystick of the
robot
malfunctioned and then the robot kept
drifting towards this l so I had to push
it just to not turn into larm po this
was not supposed to be um an experiment
to show but it turned out that was the
only experiment the only video that we
have of of pushing the robot and people
want to see pushing the robot so this is
this is the video that we have um yeah
but what's interesting is that um we
also see that these these neural
representations of the model really
capture the terrain that the the robot
is working on so here if we plot all of
them together we see that the you know
flat clusters with flat Trail clusters
with Trail and so on and we haven't
pre-programmed this either this is this
is entirely emergent um and happened as
a byproduct of learning to
walk um now Eric to answer your question
on Sample complexity so what we see is
that um that fine-tuning a model that's
pre-rain leads to better sample
complexity and training a model from
scratch and I said that this is you know
part of the benefit the other part of
the benefit is that it also leads you to
better solution than training the model
from scratch and and this is pretty
drastic in a sense that we can now train
these models in in good walking models
in about a 100 million steps um compar
compared to the our previous work on
reinforcement learning R was on the
order of 1 to 10 billion
steps and where does fine heing help
well it it helps a lot on these uneven
terrains and it helps a lot with
disturbances like pushing and and slip
so you can see here that if you if you
sort of rigorously evaluate this
pre-train model over a variety of
challenging terrains it's actually not
that great as a lot of them uh but
that's still U but that still sort of
does not prevent it from being really
helpful as a starting point for
fine so um in summary we've seen that we
can now have humanoid Locomotion over
challenging terrain terrains and we'
have uh we have this approach that
consists of two steps first pre-training
the model with sequence modeling and
then fine tuning the model with
reinforcement learning um and um that is
the the last slide I had and I think
maybe I can
say comment so so what is
missing so what huh Vision exactly so
that's the next step the final frontier
can you do with a humanoid walking with
vision not just stairs because I think
stairs will not be that hard but like
stepping
stones right or uh parkour or uh you
know uh just in some unknown terrain
which is uh so essentially the way uh
you know James Bond runs after a villain
in a movie okay or Tom Cruz in Mission
Impossible you want your humanoid robot
to be able to do that using vision
so that is left as an exercise to the
gentle
reader okay and uh I think
uh yeah so we'll send you some links uh
I I thought I would have a mini lecture
on uh the the approaches used by the
folks in in Boston Dynamics and MPC so
Scott gasma Ross R tedrick you know Mar
but that line of work but I think
uh we'll just give you references and
you can uh you can read them
yourself okay so the lecture is over
thank you